Rasmus Borgsmidt

Independent Software Consultant, BCS from University of Copenhagen (DIKU)

About me

Currently working as a software consultant on customer projects.

Nearly 20 years of experience as a software professional, for the most part building financial planning software for the enterprise. Lead developer and maintainer for many years of the J Calculation Engine, a component central to most operations in **IBM Cognos Planning**. Also co-invented several key features of this product.

Bachelor of Computer Science from University of Copenhagen (1994–1997, 2010–2014). A bachelor's thesis was submitted in June 2013 and was graded 12 (top mark). The thesis titled *Functional Array Programming Compiled to a Virtual Machine*, may be downloaded from http://borgsmidt.dk/public/functional_array_programming.pdf.

Named inventor and co-inventor on several issued patents.

Experience with a broad suite of technologies and methodologies, including Java 8, C#, JavaScript, Erlang, Ruby, APL/J, functional programming languages, as well as runtime code generation of MSIL, JBC and x86 machine code.

Enjoys tinkering with JavaScript, Erlang and Ruby — and AngularJS, which has brought a clean and healthy sense of modularity and code separation to the world of clientside JavaScript.

Avid practitioner of test-driven development and similar outside-in modes of thought.

Experience as Team Captain and Scrum Master of a highly distributed development group with members across four time zones.

Lived five years abroad in the UK and Luxembourg.

Specialties: Enterprise software development, calc/modeling engines, object model design, API design, financial planning software, collaboration, object-oriented analysis and design, test-driven development, dynamic code generation, structured refactoring and performance optimization.

Contact

+45 71 77 03 23

rasmus@borgsmidt.dk linkedin.com/in/borgsmidt github.com/borgsmidt

References available upon request

Experience

Lead Developer (Consultant), KMD, 2015-Present

In this role, I split my time between software development and enabling a Polish team of developers to

deliver the required functionality. The task is to deliver a set of SOAP web services for KOMBIT Støttesystemer (STS).

Technologies: OIO standards, SOAP web services, XML, XSD, XSLT 2, Java 8, Hibernate/ORM, WildFly, Liquibase, FreeMarker, IntelliJ, Eclipse, Jira, Git, Stash, Gradle, Bamboo, SoapUl, YourKit Profiler, LogPoint

Owner, Independent Software Engineer, Code Matters, 2014-Present

As an independent software engineer, I work as a consultant on customer projects and spend my spare time building up my own software projects.

Sr Software Engineer, IBM, 2009-2015

In this role, my primary responsibility was refining and maintaining the calc engine at the heart of the **IBM Cognos Planning** enterprise software solution. I also contributed to the development of other related products and occasionally went on-site for beta testing and the like.

Technologies: Java, C#, J/APL, JavaScript, Python, Eclipse, Visual Studio, Rational Team Concert, Rational Clear Quest

Scrum Master for Distributed Team, IBM, 2009–2012

In addition to my development responsibilities, I served as *Scrum Master/Team Captain* of a distributed scrum team with members across four time zones.

Technologies: Rational Team Concert, Rational Clear Quest

Sr Software Engineer, Cognos, 2003-2008

In this role, my primary responsibility was building and maintaining core server components of the **Cognos Enterprise Planning** enterprise software solution. In addition to this, I was heavily involved in research projects that later resulted in a series of patents.

Technologies: Java, C#, J/APL, Python, Eclipse, Visual Studio, Perforce, x86 machine code, Java Bytecode, MSIL (.NET Bytecode), XSLT

QA Technician / Software Engineer, Adaytum, 1997-2002

In my initial role at Adaytum, I worked in 3rd-level support and with test bed development. Then my responsibilities shifted and I started contributing directly to the **Adaytum Planning** software product, most notably the introduction and development of **Adaytum e.Planning/Contributor**.

Technologies: J/APL, Visual Basic, Visual Studio, x86 machine code

Education

Bachelor of Computer Science, University of Copenhagen, 2010–2014

A bachelor's thesis was submitted June 2013 and was graded 12 (top mark). The thesis titled *Functional Array Programming Compiled to a Virtual Machine* is available upon request. GPA 11.05 of 12.

Bachelor of Computer Science and Maths, University of Copenhagen, 1994–1998

This education was cut short after being hired into Adaytum.

Skills

Programming

Experience with a host of languages, such as Java, Ruby, C#, JavaScript, Haskell, SML, Erlang, C, Python, J/APL, MSIL, Java Bytecode, assembly language, binary machine code—the list goes on.

Methodology

Keen proponent of *outside-in* design principles, such as *test-driven development*, and the importance of small teams, incremental delivery and iterative processes in general. Respects the art and craft of software engineering, and takes pride in continuous integration and refactoring.

Languages

Speaks and writes Danish and English with native proficiency, German with elementary proficiency.

Personality

Character

Always curious, generally well-liked, can have a meaningful conversation with people from all walks of life. Handles pressure well and makes a point of doing things the right way.

- team player
- thorough
- creative
- analytic
- leads by example
- professional

Interests

- Object models and REST
- Concurrent programming (Erlang/OTP)
- Dynamic and functional languages
- Building grammars and DSLs
- Cloud technologies
- Raspberry Pi
- Network security and anonymity
- Photography
- Classic computer emulation
- Go (ancient strategic boardgame)

Patents

Scalable mechanism for resolving cell-level access from sets of dimensional access rules, 2013, uspatno. 8,538,990

Techniques for resolving cell-level access in a multi-dimensional data structure based on one or more

sets of dimensional access rules.

Rasmus Borgsmidt, David Bowen, Kirk Bates

Automatically moving annotations associated with multi-dimensional data between

live data cubes, 2013, uspatno. 8,347,207

Techniques for sharing multi-dimensional data and associated annotations between software systems.

Rasmus Borgsmidt, Finuala Barnes, Bindhu Cherian

Enterprise planning and performance management system providing type-safe

retrieval of multi-dimensional data, 2011, uspatno. 7,895,150

Techniques for ensuring type safety at compile time of multi-dimensional data retrieval.

Rasmus Borgsmidt, Michael Gould

Job scheduling for automatic movement of multi-dimensional data between live data cubes, 2011, uspatno. 7,877,355

Techniques for sharing multi-dimensional data between software systems.

Rasmus Borgsmidt, David Bowen

Virtual multi-dimensional datasets for enterprise software systems, 2010, uspatno.

7,747,562

Techniques for specifying virtual datasets within an enterprise software system.

Rasmus Borgsmidt, Michael Gould

Multi-dimensional data cube validation, 2009, uspatno. 7,610,294

Techniques for validating data that a user enters into a multi-dimensional data cube within an enterprise software system.

Rasmus Borgsmidt